Guide to the Cardwell and Irwin families collection 2021.002
Center for Brooklyn History
Cardwell and Irwin families collection
1860-1924
1860-1910
Center for Brooklyn History
Cardwell, John Crean
Parker, Grace Ann
2021.002
1.75 Linear Feet in 3 legal manuscript boxes and one small flat box.
The bulk of this collection consists of handwritten correspondence between John Crean Cardwell and Grace Ann Parker, dating 1891-1897. Regular correspondence also dates 1900-1905, when Grace lived in Switzerland and New York State to receive treatment for tuberculosis. The letters discuss John's medical practice, details about patients and treatments, and daily life in Brooklyn and Worcester, Massachusetts. Cardwell and Parker also discuss their relationship, plan for their 1897 wedding, and discuss various friends and family members. Also included is a photograph album, presumably compiled by Grace's nephew's grandmother-in-law, Anna Maria Conselyea after she married into the Irwin family.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of this collection consists of handwritten correspondence between John Crean Cardwell and Grace Ann Parker, dating 1891-1897. Regular correspondence also dates 1900-1905, when Grace lived in Switzerland and New York State to receive treatment for tuberculosis. The letters discuss John's medical practice, details about patients and treatments, and daily life in Brooklyn and Worcester, MA. Cardwell and Parker also discuss their relationship, plan for their 1897 wedding, and discuss various friends and family members.
Additional correspondence includes John's friend Nathan Breiler, Grace's cousin Lilian Parker, Grace's half sister Gertrude Parker, and her father Henry Langdon Parker. The collection also inlcudes the couple's 1897 wedding invitation and Grace's 1906 medical test results.
Also included is a photograph album, presumably compiled by Grace's nephew's grandmother-in-law, Anna Maria Conselyea after she married into the Irwin family. Portraits show members of the Irwin, Conselyea, McFarlane, Webb, and Darling families dating circa 1860-1879. Notable portraits include a distant cousin of the Irwin family, Charles Sherwood Stratton, better known by his stage name, Tom Thumb and photograph of President Abraham Lincoln with his son Tad. There is no known relationship between the Lincoln and Irwin families.
Accompanying the photograph album is a detailed report by donor Anne Hornung-Soukup, printed by the archivist, with biographical information about the sitters and a family tree outlining relationships. A photograph of William Henry Irwin also includes detailed biographical information provided by Hornung-Soukup.
Biographical Note
John Crean Cardwell (1866-1940) was born in Philadelphia, PA to George Cardwell, a store clerk, and Margaretta Richards. John attended the Bellevue Hospital Medical College, and later taught neurology and physiology at Harvard Medical School from 1891-1893, before returning to Brooklyn and becoming a practicing physician. Grace Ann Parker (1866-1941) was born in Worcester, MA to Henry Langdon Parker (1832-1910), a lawyer and Massachusetts state legislator, and Isabelle Hopewell Hayden Mason. Grace was an artist and studied at the Massachusetts Normal Art School, in Florence, Italy, and later at the Pratt Institute in Brooklyn. After she graduated she was supervisor of Art in the Worcester Public Schools for two years. John and Grace were married on June 10th, 1897, in Worcester MA. From 1900-1905 Grace spent time in Switzerland and upstate New York to receive treatment for tuberculosis.
Arrangement
Correspondence is arranged chronologically by year. Items within folders are not arranged.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Anne Soukup, the granddaughter of Grace Anne Parker's nephew Dean Huntington Parker, in 2021. Additional materials gifted in 2024.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Additional correspondence between John Crean Cardwell and Grace Ann Parker are held at the Worcester Historical Museum in Worcester, MA.
Correspondence; Physicians -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Portrait photography; Studio portraits; Photograph albums
- Photograph Album Documentation, 2025 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photograph of John Crean Cardwell, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photograph of William Henry Irwin, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  General
  Folder includes biographical information.
- Correspondence, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
- Correspondence, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
- Correspondence, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
- Correspondence, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
- Wedding Invitation, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1902-1905 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Medical Test Results, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1909-1910, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Photograph Album, circa 1860-1879 (Box 4)
  See box 1 folder 1 for biographical information and a family tree.